This is Humans.
>> Humans.
>> [music]
>> I'm Hank Green.
Today and for the last 10 years or so,
Ze Frank is well known for his True
Facts videos, where he embodies the
character of a delighted and juvenile
nature documentary host explaining
strange and wonderful animals. They are
some of the best celebrations of life
and science that I know of and I love
each one and I run to them when they
come out, but Ze also has a bit of a
secret. He is not just great at the form
of online video, he also kind of
invented it. I'm sure he will have
problems with my storytelling here.
Maybe not all of online video, but
there's this thing that we take for
granted, which is a way of making
things, video in particular, which is
very aware of how the internet actually
works and it allows for things to be
like collaborative and weird and
intimate and connecty and parasocial and
all of this stuff.
And Ze's videos on his series the show,
in which he posted a video every weekday
of 2006, made video into something that
wasn't just watched, but it like folded
back in on itself and it was not built
by Ze, it was built by all of the people
watching, including Ze. And if you go
and watch some of those episodes and you
should, you'll see what I mean when I
say that it may be among some of the
most innovative pieces of culture of all
time. I am gushing too much, of course,
but I don't really have a way of
expressing or even understanding the
depth of Ze's impact on me or his work's
impact on my work. So, I'm going to pick
two things. First, to this day, whenever
I am blocked and I don't know what to
make, I could go and watch Ze's videos
and it could be from 2006 or it could be
from 2026. Ze has a way of making things
that gets me unblocked. And second,
there's this two-minute video he once
made about how you can get addicted to
the true and perfect form of an idea in
your head and not want to expose it to
the unfortunate reality of reality, but
you need to because ideas are not for
your head. Ideas are for turning into
real things in the real world, and they
have to confront the world and be shaped
by the people who we think they are for
and by the reality they must exist
inside of. So, I want to talk to Ze
about ideas and where they come from and
what happens when you share them and
what the internet used to make possible
and what the internet makes possible now
and whether it's all terrible now and
what weird animals might teach us about
the weirdest animal of all. Ze Frank,
welcome to humans. Where do ideas come
from?
>> Well, thanks for the intro. You're right
that I probably take issue with a little
bit of that framing, but we can get into
that. This question of where ideas come
from, I think it's central to
my life and certainly a lot of other
creative people. And I think that the
importance
often comes from some sort
[clears throat] of an urgency that we
have
to not only have ideas, but to have
ideas that feel like you. In addition to
that, it's like there's one thing to
have an idea, but then there's another
thing to decide to make it. You know,
birth it. You know, I don't know how it
plays out in your mind, but I have a lot
of thoughts and have a lot of ideas and
there's a lot of possibilities and you
do have to kind of like feel them.
And feel what the possibility space is
around them.
You know, that's something that I think
you get better at over a creative life
is having an instinct for the shape of
an idea and whether or not it has the
qualities that you know, are going to
mature into something or kind of allow
you to play around in a way that
feels right.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you know, in a lot of cases I'll sit
on stuff for for years even.
>> Because I don't have the shape of the
thing. There's a short video I did
called damselfly and beetle. I got this
footage and it's a damselfly [snorts]
that comes out of a kind of a murky pond
and rests on a hickory nut that's
floating.
And she just went through her final
molt, right? And so her wings have to
dry before she takes off. So she's just
hanging out. And this beetle comes up
and it joins her. And they have this
beautiful little interaction and then
the beetle leaves and then a male
damselfly comes up and eats her wings,
which is kind of common.
And so she now is wingless. She's
she's done. And the final shot is her
kind of climbing back down
into the stew of the pond. And it's it
was so
kind of profound in a way that I just
didn't understand. I mean, I knew it was
profound when I looked at it cuz it
encapsulated almost everything that that
I feel like is important, right? There
was some humor in it. There was some
pathos and then there was this
incredible pain.
>> I have wings now, [music] beetle. I'm
going to live up there.
I have wings, damselfly. I can show you.
I can come with you.
>> [music]
>> Oh, beetle, you know you can't leave the
muck.
After that, beetle moved far away.
He found work at a small hotel running
the front desk.
>> [music]
>> And it took me probably almost almost 3
years to come up with a narrative that I
thought kind of did it justice.
>> A thing that I hear there is a little
bit like like why is that something that
goes from I have this and I've seen it
and I've experienced it to I want to
make something along with this. I want
to create like there's a little bit of a
why and I I run into this sometimes when
I'm like, "Ooh." And I'd tell somebody
the idea I have. They're like, "Oh, I'm
so glad that you want to do that." You
know, we want to create
in the ways that we're comfortable, but
also in that is achieving some kind of
goal. And there is just a an urge.
You know, like I have this urgency
sometimes where I have to make
something. I've got many other things
that are much more pressing. People are
waiting on me. There like better
economic incentives to do something
else, but I'm I have to make this thing
because I've had the idea. The urge is
just internal.
But, it's also an urge to like make
something that somebody will see and
react to.
>> Right.
I mean, I think you said a lot of
different things that are interesting
there. I'm going [snorts] to go back to
the first one that caught my ear, which
was we want to make things that are
comfortable.
And I don't know if I agree with that
for me personally. I actually feel like
I want to make things that are
uncomfortable.
>> Do you want to make things that are
uncomfortable for you?
>> For me to make. You know, generally the
there's stuff that kind of comes easy to
you. And this is
you know, everybody knows this is that
you know, you get frustrated with people
for not doing the stuff that they can
just do, right?
And here here's the sort of like you
know, make another funny thing. Come on.
Like
>> Play the hits.
>> Yeah, yeah, exactly. I think that making
things is about becoming. That's the joy
of it is is that you you see something
develop and birth. You feel yourself
getting better through the struggle. You
feel like some kind of emergence that
happened. Like there's a journey. And um
comfort to me is usually a sign that
you're
off from the meat of it.
>> Hmm.
>> There's a really practical way that I've
been thinking about that lately. And
that is
especially as you know, later in your
career later in life, you have
certain lanes that you can occupy very
comfortably, right? Let's just call them
like your dominant domains, whatever
that means. There comes a point where
you realize that those domains like
don't get you everything. They don't get
you the full picture, right? So, guitar
playing for me, I've spent long time
playing guitar. I've toured with a band.
I
had a whole previous life as a musician.
But, I used my dominant domain to do it,
right? Visual. So, one thing that you
can do to learn keys and what is
appropriate to play at a particular time
is to memorize patterns on the board.
So, you memorize shapes that you know
all those notes roughly will work.
If somebody says this is in the key of
E, it's blues, I know the shape on the
fretboard that corresponds with what
will sound right.
And so, that's called pattern playing.
It's a way for you to become very
proficient without necessarily having
trained your ear. You're not using your
auditory connection as much. And so,
about 3 years ago I made the promise to
myself that I would never look at at the
fretboard of my guitar again.
>> Woah. So, you're you're imposing this
constraint on yourself.
>> I'm imposing the constraint on myself so
that my dominant domain doesn't get
involved and it wants to. Like, even
internally when I'm playing, listening
to something and playing over it, I have
to
almost scold myself because I very
quickly just imagine looking at the
thing. I see I see it in my mind and I
go right back into that dominant domain.
So, one of the things about learning,
which is kind of interesting, is and I
think this applies to like when you're,
you know, deciding to make something is
paying attention to the areas that are
interesting that you're sort of like,
"Ah, I don't know a way into it that
way." You know, I know a way into it
this way.
I mean, this is kind of abstract, but I
think that that's where a lot of joy
comes from.
>> I'm hearing a lot
that resonates with how I imagine
ideation, which for me is often a
process of, you know, understanding the
problem space, you know, that that
problem space might be like something
that's really annoying me about the
world right now, like that, you know,
Congress thinks that there's UFOs or
something. And so, lots of people around
me are like, "Hank, what do you think
about UFOs?" cuz I'm a science guy. And
I'm like, "I need to make something
about this. I need to make something
about why we go off in this direction. I
need to make something about why this is
like such a common hypothesis, but often
ends up being a an incorrect hypothesis.
And so, like I I like feel the problem
space. And then I look at my toolkit.
And the thing about a toolkit is that
it's not You weren't born with it. And
so, every like thing in there was
created for me. I mean, not everything,
but but most of the things in my toolkit
were created by me needing to solve a
problem and not having a tool to solve
it and then like developing that tool
through discomfort in a lot of
situations. But there is a time when it
feels a little like maybe my toolkit's
pretty full. I've got these dominant
domains. I can solve a lot of problems
with them. You look at like every
problem through the lens of your own
toolkit. Whereas, what I'm hearing from
you is like there is this urge to always
make sure that you're staying a little
uncomfortable because something else is
going to come out of that. Because where
you're learning, and this is I think
very true of of most people, like you
learn most things in the doing,
not in the like reading about it and and
developing the skills. Like you learn
more ultimately touring with a band than
you do playing scales.
>> Uh, yes. I guess I'm cautious to kind of
put words like you learn more or things
like that. It depends on what kind of an
experience you want to have in your
creative life and to some degree it's a
little bit of a luxury to be in the
space maybe that we are where we get to
like, you know, say like I want my
experience doing it to be like this or
like this. You know, when everybody's
like, don't be afraid to fail. Like,
yeah, well, if you don't have a lot of
money, yeah, be afraid to fail because
you don't have that choice.
>> I think about like things where I see
people having like effortless expertise
like surfing. You know, I've never
surfed. And so I look at people surfing
and I'm like, wow, that looks very good.
It looks like it would be very good to
be able to do that. But like you don't
get good at surfing by being good at
surfing, you know?
>> Right, right, right, right.
>> And you have to kind of be okay with the
idea of absolutely getting smashed
sometimes and slapping your face on the
board or whatever other things happen
that's unpleasant while you're surfing.
>> Yeah.
>> Um social interactions probably also. I
think that would keep me away from
surfing honestly. Just feeling like I
don't know how to do this. All these
people are looking at me. I don't want
to make them mad at me. There's rules I
don't know.
>> I hear you 100% [laughter] and like that
to me right now is the most interesting
stuff. It's like
getting into positions where you really
can fail. Just to bring it into the kind
of practical realm. I think that
like let's take science communication,
you know, for example. You know, you
mentioned that there's a toolbox of
things associated with your past and how
you learn. Uh there's also the toolbox
of content and culture at large, right?
I mean, so we imitate quite a bit. The
thing that excites me about episodes is
kind of the thing that I think terrifies
a lot of people when they take on a
subject that is new to them. And that is
stumbling into something that I
genuinely don't understand.
I mean, I'll give you an example. Like
an episode on camels, it was a wonderful
one for me because I you know, there was
this nice piece of footage where there's
a garden hose, you know, and there's the
water that's just dumping into this
camel, you know. And you you've heard
the line so many times, like they can
drink up to a blah blah blah gallons a
day, you know, like that's amazing.
But, at that moment I was like, "Oh,
[__] Where does the water go?"
Like, [laughter]
>> It's really going in.
>> Yeah, where where does it go? Like,
first of all, if they just held it
internally, their stomach would distend.
And then it was like, "Oh, crap. Like,
if they actually ingest all that water
into their bloodstream, I mean, if we
did that, we would die. All our cells
would burst." That was like 3 weeks into
the episode. It might have take a long
time to make these things. But but all
of a sudden I was like, "Oh, crap." But
that's like the best part.
>> Yeah, it's such a delight. Also, you
know, to have the toolkit necessary to
be able to say that, to know that, to be
able to be like, "What's the weird thing
here?"
>> Yeah.
>> Which comes from spending time
understanding how things work, which is
such a joy to have that be part of my
work.
It's interesting to me that you ended up
in that direction. So, there was a there
was kind of a period of time on the Ze
Frank channel where, you know, you were
kind of doing your follow-up show, you
were kind of doing that video on trust
with the Cirque du Soleil acrobats.
You're like just sort of doing things,
you know, that the human tests.
These are all like videos where you are
in a sense like essay writing, creating
art, just trying out ideas.
True Facts was mixed in during that
time. And it's interesting to me that
the thing that came out of it, you sort
of like narrowed it on the science
communication as the thing
that you would do. Do you have any idea
why?
>> It's a little bit like
a roulette wheel. If I'm like
maybe in my
what I envision is my best kind of
creative place.
The roulette wheel's spinning, man. And
like, you know, I'm the ball and I'm
just like bouncing and I'm like hitting
all over the place and it's exciting and
you're kind of looking everywhere and
and then there's, you know, there's
moments where the roulette wheel stops.
You know, for me it was COVID. Life just
was a lot harder. Everything
just required a hell of a lot more
effort.
>> Like social or was this health stuff?
>> Oh, not health stuff. No, it was it was
the political environment. It was the
fact that we were in a pandemic and and
didn't know what was going to happen.
There was an you know, in a sort of a
very big oppressive weight.
There are times where when we were
talking about dominant domains and
things like that, you know, like go
right for what you know. Like because
you just don't have the energy and you
know, True Facts,
I [snorts] remember back in the day, you
know, we had a conversation and you
said, you know, like I uh the problem
with True Facts, you're going to run out
of animals.
>> And now That doesn't sound like
something I'd say now, but there's yeah,
there's some limitations, but yeah.
>> I did one uh I think called that uh the
first one was like on the hedgehog and
it was all like made up. It was just
there were no facts in it whatsoever.
And then I started on another one and I
was like, oh [__] coming up with like
abstract jokes about footage, I'm going
to hit a wall so quick because then
you're just going to see the limitations
of my innate humor skills.
>> And and also like you don't want people
to think that you're telling them true
facts when they aren't true facts.
There's this like you could do it with
certain animals, but like when you start
to get to weird animals, people are
like, I guess maybe.
I guess maybe.
>> Right, right, right, right. I don't even
think that that crossed my mind because
True Facts was a send-up, right? The
whole thing was supposed to be a send-up
of how serious nature documentaries took
themselves and
>> Well, and it is still sort of is.
>> Well, it's kind of circled back, right?
But that's why I started getting into
science as fodder for jokes.
That was literally it. I was like, "The
only way that I'm going to be able to
write jokes is if I have some kind of
context to pop off." And then that over
time became the became more and more and
more of the draw.
>> And now it's like very science-y.
>> Yeah.
The reason that I like that format is
that like you can take it anywhere. The
second that you have a character which
is a host that
>> Uh-huh.
>> is very willing to break the rules. And
then, you know, over time I created yet
another character, this Jerry character
that actually subverts the video itself.
Like
>> For the listeners, Jerry is like the
writer of the scripts and the producer
of the show. And
>> Yeah, Jerry does everything. I mean,
it's it's it's kind of unclear what what
I do, you know, in [laughter] the show
sometimes. But he comes in and out as as
a vehicle for for kind of
>> comic relief
>> extending things. Yeah, it's comic
relief, but it's also like
trying to like bust things open and and
make them kind of you know, unexpected
and uncomfortable. But so anyways, yeah,
during that time it was like I needed
that. I needed the the science piece was
awesome because
you know, they're solvable problems.
>> Yeah.
I feel like that is part of how I've
ended up where I am, too. Where I'm just
like, you know, if if we're going to be
in a world of like terrible information,
it's nice to be focusing on the thing
which is primary goal is to uncover
actual truth, to like reflect reality as
accurately as possible, and has
developed a bunch of tools for actually
doing that fairly well.
>> Yeah, yeah, totally. And there's
something very nice about that. I mean,
I just, you know, I'm doing geckos right
now and I have been spending a lot of
time on that because it's, you know,
pretty complicated stuff. And I got a
note from one of the reviewing
scientists. Every episode is reviewed
by, you know, a number of scientists.
And it was like, you know,
"Good job. Couldn't find anything that,
you know, isn't supported by science."
And, you know, it tickles that
adolescent want to be the teacher's pet
thing. I got an A from the scientist.
>> There's something interesting about it
also not being I mean, now I feel like
all of your work is to some extent like
your public facing work is to some
extent
not a significant fraction of who say
actually is, whereas what I do is
probably a pretty significant fraction
of who Hank actually is.
But, you know, True Facts being a
character-based thing, a voice-based
thing, you're you are this man, you're
British.
>> I don't think that I am.
>> not?
>> It's so interesting. People call it
British. You know what I'm trying to
emulate is actually
>> Mid-Atlantic? What are you?
>> No, it So, I heard recordings of what
the kind of American Philadelphia accent
sounded like about 100 years ago.
[clears throat]
>> Okay.
>> And it has it has British qualities in
it, but it's it is distinctly American.
>> Okay. You're a 100-year-old
Philadelphian.
>> Now, if you don't know what a beetle is,
it's basically an insect that well, they
can be a bit much, all right? Like look
at Pepper here walking all distracted
like she's trying to remember the
grocery list she forgot back at the
house. Come on, you see it. But look at
what she's wearing. It's like 10:00 a.m.
and she's out in a fancy housecoat like
that. And then this, zip, pulls a
freaking Buzz Lightyear. And that's with
a lot of them, too. You know, [music]
can't just fly, has to be a whole
production like those Transformer
movies.
>> People say like that's the worst British
accent ever, and I would totally agree.
I'm not bad at accents. I could go
British if you need me to, but
>> [laughter]
>> but that's not what it is. It's a way of
speaking that really really enjoys each
syllable.
>> And the aping of the form of the sort of
like we're going to make fun of this,
but now it is just the
I don't know. I don't feel like it even
is anymore. I feel like, you know,
obviously this guy is juvenile,
obviously like this is something that uh
is if it's made for children, it's made
for children who are being a little
transgressive, maybe a 10-year-old, but
also the 10-year-old inside of all of
us.
But, still, now it does feel straight-up
a celebration of science and of how
science actually works and also of how
bizarre our world is.
>> Yeah, definitely. I mean, it's it's kind
of like just evolved, you know, I mean,
you can kind of like go back and look at
some of the earlier episodes where it's
a little more obvious what I was going
after, you know, like the armadillo
episode is I think
Oh, the armadillo episode is probably
the most foundational in terms of
creating a lot of the forms that would
be copied later on.
>> Armadillos are the last surviving
members [music] of the order Cingulata,
the armored New World mammals. Back when
animals were more badass, there were
more Cingulata, like the two-ton
glyptodont [music]
and the smaller pampatheriidae, which
could fart fire and teleport 2 in in any
direction. Who did this research? Jerry?
Oh, jeez.
>> That one, it was very much about like I
was pissed off. I mean, I like
literally, I was pissed off because I'd
seen some Discovery Channel things where
they were using metaphors about, you
know, a wolf tracking a moose and it was
like s- it stops to smell the bacteria.
It knows it's wounded and only has
another couple days left. I was like,
"Bullshit. That's just not true. If you
want to like really experience the
majesty of nature, you can't imagine
them as like slightly dumb people
thinking things like that. You have to
imagine what consciousness might be
without the burden of of language and
long-term memory and our connections.
And so, that one, you know, there's lots
of attempts of like making metaphors
like falling into a pit full of boners,
which is still one of my favorite lines.
>> But, it is vulnerable to the leg sweep
or stepping on a tiny land mine or
falling into a pit [music] of boners.
All right, that doesn't exist. No, I do
understand. I mean, just Yes, [music]
it's technically vulnerable to that, but
I'm saying there is no such thing as a
pit of boners in nature. It's It's not a
threat.
>> All right, I'll keep going, but Jerry's
an idiot.
>> [laughter]
>> You're just a little boy.
>> Oh my god.
I kind of want to reach back. So, you've
been on the internet for as long as
there's been an internet to be on,
socially internet, I mean.
>> You weren't on like DARPA net or
whatever.
>> Right, right.
>> You weren't like a a researcher with the
Department of Defense, but you you have
your degree in neuroscience, and then
you you're coming out of school, you are
in a band,
and then you find this creative outlet
that nobody has yet found.
And I've heard you talk about this,
where you're creating, and this was
before video, so you're creating like
weird little pieces of media. There
isn't really another thing to say here
besides content. There's just too much
new kinds of
art and creation
right now in this period of time for
them to have all gotten their own names,
so we just lump them under the title of
content. You're making this content, and
I've heard you describe that you felt
like you were kind of part of a scene
back then. Can you flesh that scene out
and the importance of it for me? And
this is like the early 2000s or the
'90s.
>> In your intro I said, you know, there
were sort of some things that I might
kind of take issue with then.
And I you know, I think that this idea
of sort of causality in flow is one of
them that I think we all have to kind of
struggle with.
>> Causality in flow, what do you What do
you mean?
>> So, you said that in some way that I was
responsible for things. I don't think
that that's not true, but in terms of,
you know, how much and and all that,
there's nuance there. I think of it as
like, you know, imagine like there's a a
stream, and you're a bunch of pebbles in
a stream, and and the stream all of a
sudden changes. The flow moves quicker,
or there's a change in direction. Now,
there's a couple pebbles that are just
sort of situated a little differently
than others and they're they get
dislodged.
Right? They get dislodged by whatever.
Like
>> It might be personal responsibility and
choice. It might be that there is no
free will and we're all a pebble in a
upstream.
>> Yeah.
>> That's [laughter] right. That's right.
But you get pushed you sort of get
pushed. And like maybe you knock into
some other pebbles and they get pushed,
too, right? And and so now now you're
downstream and like and the stream was
going in that direction, right? You
know? And like your shape does impact
downstream, but it doesn't it's not like
it diverts the entire stream or anything
like that.
>> I agree that there's like a lack of
responsibility here, but there is like a
early identification of what's going on
that you did that was maybe harder for
people who weren't as young.
>> That's right. That's just sort of the
shape of pebble that I was, right? I
mean like I just I already had been
you know, very into the arts, very into
music, and I knew programming because of
neuroscience, right? So, I had this I
had a really great basis for being able
to take advantage of that stuff and
you know, all of that
existed within, you know, a very
dominant form of culture.
>> Mhm.
>> It was pretty static that culture. I
mean, you know, obviously there was the
'80s, the '90s and you know, different
forms of media and stuff, but culture
felt like it was a one thing and then
this felt like it was a different thing.
There was a whole group of people that
just started playing that the idea of a
scene is to some extent where
it's pre pre-economy.
>> Mhm.
>> So, it's not like, you know, you're out
there trying to out compete each other
for who is the most financially
successful. You're trying to
>> Yes.
>> kind of like out weird each other or
>> just impress each other, out reach each
other.
>> Yeah, and even the reach stuff wasn't
even there yet.
>> like reach more people, but like you
were physical reach. Like reach to new
problems that people wouldn't have
expected to be solvable with your tools.
>> Totally. Because [snorts] back then like
the true virality stuff, the big pops
that went viral, it's not like you were
like, "Oh my gosh, I want to go viral."
It was sort of like, "Oh, like that that
became viral? Why?"
>> selling out to succeed a little and also
you have to pay for the bandwidth.
>> Yeah,
>> [laughter]
>> you do have to pay for the bandwidth.
That's what was sort of exciting about
it and and still to me the thing that I
always am yearning for and looking for
are places where something is bubbling
up and doesn't quite have an industry
behind it.
>> You're still looking for that stuff?
>> Yeah, always. I mean, always trying to
find like little pockets of new stuff.
You know, thinking about it right now. I
mean, like trying to figure out like
what is
out there that's kind of interesting
because those those are the areas
especially, you know, pre-economic where
you can mess with everything. You can
change the format, you can change the
tone, you can change like all all sorts
of things.
>> And you can yeah, and that you can
change the way that the stream is going
to go. I I think about this a lot with
online video. Of course, that stream
turned out to be so powerful in a
specific direction. There's so much
energy.
We were going to end up in a
consolidated world with, you know, sort
of a few major players being the
platforms and then everybody else being
very fractured.
Because you you had so many different
domains of expertise, you know, you were
making music, you were coding, you were
making video. I think about the
the duckies. So, there was this feature
that you
I don't know how far along the show. At
a certain point, a video would upload
and you could buy like a little duck
under the video. And that and then you
you would And so, this is like a very
early crowdfunding vibe.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> And like that just changes the economics
of online videos so much. And of course
this later came along with Patreon to
some extent, but the idea that maybe
this wouldn't be advertising funded,
probably that just isn't possible. Like
probably this was always going to be
advertising funded. But it just makes me
think that
it could have gone other directions
maybe.
Like I just saw you innovating in ways
that it didn't feel like the platforms
could or would.
But I guess probably what happened is
that the dominant thing that was going
to work the best is what we ended up
with.
>> [snorts]
>> Do you think that that is true? Do you
think we could have ended up in a
different world?
>> Yeah, so the the buy the duckies thing
was developed by a guy named Eric that,
you know, worked on some of the really
intensely complex stuff. You know, the
tool where you where you found the
opposite on the globe for the earth
sandwich.
>> Uh-huh. An- another thing that Xay did
during the show is he turned the earth
into a sandwich by having two people on
the opposite sides of the globe find the
exact opposite sides of the globe and
put a piece of bread on the ground on
each side.
>> Yeah, I had that thought like on a
plane, but I had no clue how how to, you
know, execute the complexity of of
actually finding your your antipity. You
know, so I don't know
I don't know.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't know the answer to that
question. I don't know if it could have
gone a lot of different ways. What I do
know is that certainly there's a
framework for looking at the world where
elite people, people with a lot of money
and power take over
things. Uh there's a really interesting
book called Elite Capture that actually
has to do with
not the economics side, but it's a a way
of of thinking about people who are
disenfranchised and and the language
that the left often uses, you know, to
try to kind of pull that conversation
into them politically.
But I mean I I think that that's
something that happens over and over and
over and over over again in history,
right? And I think that yes, there were
probably different possible futures, but
that one probably was almost guaranteed
because of that pattern that we're in.
And I do think that it you know,
once that ball gets rolling, the scene
is lost because it's just not there. I
think that, you know, you you had
written to me about, you know, is the
internet tainted now?
You know, it just doesn't exist. The
internet that we were playing in just
doesn't exist. It's gone. That the the
world of permalinks and web links and
websites and and all that kind of stuff
has been completely swallowed up by
social.
And I don't think of it necessarily as
worse or better for the world. There's
things that are worse and better for me,
certainly. And one of the biggest ones
is that
you know, we've moved away from
searching out content to just passively
waiting for it to appear again because
of signals that we give some unknown
thing, right? Some algorithm.
>> Yeah, we're giving them signals and they
have their own their own goals as well,
which is, you know, largely to keep us
on the website.
>> That's right. But in that way, like the
second that people don't sort of like
and and obviously this isn't true for
everyone, but you know, if if people
kind of lose that instinct of looking
for stuff. Have you done more? Are you
still doing stuff? I mean, the the
comments that are are so sort of
puzzling and or at least like point to
this are like, "Oh my gosh, you're doing
content again." And it's like, "What?"
Kind of never stopped. I just I just
wasn't in your feed, bro.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, yeah. I haven't seen you in so
long. And I'm like, I don't know what to
say. That's how it works now. That's
>> [laughter]
>> That's going to be true for a lot of
people at any given moment. Oh my god,
there's so many things I want to talk to
you about, but you were talking about
that beginnings of virality. You like
went viral before like in the sort of
earliest times of virality when it was
email based. So like I'd get an email
forward from someone and it's like look
the Dutch exploded this whale that was
on the beach and it didn't go as planned
which is a great title for a YouTube
video. And you had a couple of these
things that were not like America's
Funniest Home Video clips but things you
created that were funny and weird and
went viral and then like you've kept
going viral kind of the whole time which
makes me think that it does matter to
you.
>> There is something about it that
is satisfying. Uh less so now certainly.
I mean my relationship with the
platforms has changed so much. Like you
know
when I release something on YouTube it I
just sort of release it. I mean I used
to just sit there and wait for comments
and like
>> Someday I will reach your level of
enlightenment Z.
>> [laughter]
>> I still go back to it but it doesn't
feel I mean it feels less connected you
know
to me or the work or or things like
that. I feel like I've put it into a
mall and then people are kind of like
walking by and looking at it and stuff.
And that's not to say that I there isn't
like a group of people that I have a
closer connection to like Patreon for
example. But yeah I mean like you know
TikTok the creepy Dave thing you know
>> Do Creepy Dave for a second so we all
know what Creepy Dave is.
>> He's like a a mixture between uh Strong
Bad Dr. Steve Brule and then maybe
Triumph the Insult Comic Dog. What is
he's like
it's Creepy Dave.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. That guy. He's a little stupid.
He's happy. He gets happy.
>> There's something joyful about a lot of
your work which is interesting because I
do get the impression that you are
somewhat sullen
natured.
>> Yeah [laughter] I am. I am actually.
Yeah I'm actually incredibly serious. I
think it's like a a radical
disappointment for a lot of people that
meet me. [laughter]
>> I remember the first time we hung out in
in the real world, and I wouldn't say
that I came I would I definitely would
not say I came away disappointed, but I
came away very thoughtful. Every
conversation we have ever had, I think
about years later.
Just a refreshing set
of perspectives, and always not so
informed by
like whatever the hell is going on in
the internet. You know, it just seems
like a lot of thinking is oriented
toward whatever is being risen to the
top by algorithms,
and I never feel that when I'm talking
to you. But, I'm interested in this sort
of joyful nature of a lot of your
characters.
>> They merge different qualities, right?
That was a little bit of the problem
with Creepy Dave. I mean, I stopped
doing it as much. If you actually go
through and and watch them, you see that
there's all these attempts to talk about
the human condition in them, but through
his bizarre lens. And that was me trying
to like find some basis of purpose
inside that character.
>> Right, some reason you were actually
doing it instead of just like, "I'm
getting views." Yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah. It's not an easy one
to kind of go through, but
>> in in general, the short form is very
hard to get to something
where I feel
super proud of the things that go super
wide.
>> There's a woman named Caitlin Cowell,
who joined me on True Facts maybe three
or four years ago. And I worked with her
a long time ago. And she kind of was on
me about short form. And I was sort of
like, "Ah, I can't. I It's like, you
know,
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, partially partially because I
knew like at that time the dominant idea
was that short form was marketing for
long form. And I knew because of the
work that I did at BuzzFeed, that that's
just not true. I mean, I'd seen the
stats like at scale, like at at the
billion view scale.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I was kind of hesitant and things
like that. And then I was like, all
right, fine, I'll kind of play. And so,
at first I was just launching clips and
stuff. And I was like, all right, let me
let me like palpate it a little bit.
>> Understand the thing, yeah.
>> Yeah. And so, I did the thing that I
kind of always do, which is make some
sort of assumptions about what you think
is sort of in the vibe of that space.
And then I released like a few things.
There was one which was the heron that
is trying to catch the fishes.
>> Little fishies, are you afraid of the
dark? It's night time now. Go to bed. Go
to bed. Everybody go to bed. Yeah, I'm
just kidding with you.
>> The voice starts to kind of take shape a
little bit.
>> Mhm.
>> And then there was this one, this
vulture. He he fit all those little
characteristics.
>> Here comes a creepy Dave.
That's what people call me.
How you doing? Okay, you walk away.
Uh-oh.
Creepy Dave made a peepee.
He's everywhere.
Whoopsie.
Creepy Dave.
>> It was like, oh, okay, this is a, you
know, a character. It did well. So, now
let's think of a format that you can
kind of put it in and and move forward.
>> Right. So, you're not making like clips
from long-form video. You're making
short-form video. You're understanding
what people are responding to. You're
building
>> Yeah.
>> a thing. You're creating in that space.
You're innovating. It is so impressive
to me, though.
Like Creepy Dave doesn't rely on any
previous
Zay Frank fame.
Your success does not rely on your
previous successes. It feels like you
try and get out of a box every time and
do a little bit of building from
scratch, which is
impossible. It's so rare to be able to
build
a strong audience. And so, it really is
like an indication
that there is a skill set here that you
are good at. Cuz I often feel like my
own career, I was like, I don't know how
to get famous on YouTube. I know how to
do it in 2007, but like now, how would I
do it? I don't know. It's so hard. Do
you feel an urge to try and separate
your
eras, your pieces of content from your
previous creations and also your
previous brands or imaginings, like how
people imagine you?
>> As you were talking, I was trying to I
was reversing the question and I was
like
thinking like, well, why
>> [laughter]
>> why do I do that? Especially the way you
said it, it sounds like such a pain in
the ass.
Right, yeah, like, oh, [__] [laughter]
I I do think that I I get uncomfortable
by constraints.
I mean, I think that
when you make work that is viewed by a
lot of people, you have this interesting
relationship with the content and the
people, and they have an interesting
relationship with the content and you.
And that triangle, it has kind of
characteristics to it. I think in the
worst cases
for me, people start thinking that you
are the content and that feels very
uncomfortable.
>> Right. I mean, with the show, it was so
much Z. It was Z's ideas, Z's analysis
of the news. I It's crazy when you go
back and watch and see how much of the
show is news.
>> Yeah.
But it wasn't really me, right? I mean,
like it was some momentary thing that
came together.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think that there's people and I
think you're certainly one of them that
is
more more comfortable kind of being
yourself.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and I don't know what that means
exactly, but you're comfortable with
whatever tensions come out of that and
you seem to be able to separate those
things out. That's not something that
has ever come easy to me.
>> That's so interesting because like you
were like one of the first models of
doing it, you know? There was like
you're looking straight down the barrel
of the lens.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, uncomfortable.
Like what we started this conversation
on. That was like the most uncomfortable
thing that I could do and it was
it was very, very uncomfortable. That
whole that whole show was like very hard
for me.
Partially it's that I have I do have a
little bit of a fear of getting stuck in
things. I want my work
certainly to be a reflection of the
struggles and thoughts that I'm going
through at this time, where I am right
now.
And when it gets disconnected from that,
it becomes more like a job, more like
work and less of like
this discovery of, you know, who you
are, what you're capable of. And I think
that that's kind of why I pop around.
And I mean there's also like
I think I can make it pop without people
even knowing it's me, you know? Like
that's kind of cool, too.
>> It does feel like a little bit of a
flex. Was Octopus the first True Facts
that got really, really big?
>> No, I think it was Anglerfish. But
[laughter] I think Octopus predates
Anglerfish now because at that time,
this was like the very early days, I was
like, I can use any footage I want. And
then like five years later, I got hit
with, you know, a $5,000
>> Yeah, you had to take it down and put it
back up.
>> Yeah, exactly. But that switched pretty
fast because I was like, oh crap.
>> Yeah, did that feel like I still got it?
Or I've got something else, you know?
>> I mean, I think that the origin of True
Facts is kind of interesting because and
it dovetails into something that you had
asked about in the email that you sent
me, which was, you know, about the time
at BuzzFeed, which I haven't really
spent a lot of time talking about.
>> Yeah, no, I couldn't find you talking
about it anywhere.
>> Yeah, and and I, you know, I probably
won't be talking about it very much
here, either. But um
so True Facts and some of those other
kind of pieces, these sort of like
pensive pieces and things like that,
came out of when I was starting the
video
aspect of BuzzFeed and I had, you know,
at that time maybe seven, eight, nine
people working for me, you know, before
it got big. You know, the these are
talented young people who came out of
film school and one of the first things
that I had to do was like try to come up
with some framework for making things
that was in opposition to that way.
>> In opposition to what way? Like the the
film school way?
>> school way. Like segmenting the labor,
you know, even beginning, middle, and
ends, music choice, editing choices, all
this kind of stuff. So, I was
I did a a whole series of videos where I
was like, "Oh, no, you can make things
just with stock footage. You don't have
to be on camera. You don't have to use
anything." And so, True Facts was was
part of that. Was me trying to show
people what the possibilities were.
>> Jonah Peretti asked you to like run
BuzzFeed Video. You came and did that.
It's just such a deeply different thing
from creating in your own head, making
stuff, testing it out, iterating super
fast. For years you made stuff every
day, popping it out into the world and
seeing how people would respond to it,
just getting the ideas out of your head,
to collaborating, to like leading
creative people to try and have them
create these things. This must have been
a very different thing.
>> The beginning was very consistent with
>> Mhm.
>> the rest of what I did. I mean, we had a
small team of people, you know, even up
to like 20 people. This is just the
first year or so.
It was like
we made so much media so quickly. We
created a whole new sort of framework
for how you brainstorm.
And we were just like making stuff all
the time and talking about it all the
time and there was a powerful kind of
feeling because it really felt like we
were doing it different. And the
philosophy, simply put, I mean, it was
pretty complicated, but [laughter]
the velocity simply put was that most
people's experiences are not reflected
in media. Think about all the
experiences that aren't really reflected
in popular media and make video about
it. So, that included all sorts of
things and it felt like this wide-open
playground and the first year or two
felt very consistent with what I was
doing, but you know, I didn't have an HR
department and like once you creep up
into like a hundred people and like you
can't all fit in the same room and then
that's where I was at really the limits
of what comes naturally to me and you
know, I had to start learning some other
things. You know, from that point
forward I was well outside my comfort
zone and never really got comfortable
with the experience.
>> Yeah, there's also just the element of
being like a leader of a company that's
in the public and you're going to events
and you're speaking on behalf of the
company and you're sort of towing
company line and like trying to figure
out how to be like one of the big
fast-growing parts of a of an
organization that's theoretically needs
to keep growing big and fast so it can
keep getting investors forever, which
obviously long-term hasn't worked out.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that whole framework rate of
business aesthetic and mimicking certain
things in the way you speak or like you
just said towing the company line, which
you know, kind of implies that
>> You don't necessarily agree with it.
>> Or or it's not your thought, you know,
it's it's another thought and and then
you have to answer questions as if you
were wherever that thought came from,
you know, and
that's a lot less fun. But you know, the
the beginning of it was incredible. I
mean, like I count it as one of the most
exciting times that I've had.
>> Would you ever do anything like that
again?
>> I mean, I'd love to work with people. I
don't really want to create a big
organization that has an ultimate goal
of making a lot of money for rich
investors.
That I don't I'm not really interested
in, but but yeah, absolutely. I would
like to interact with folks a little bit
more.
>> Coming out of that, is there
uh kind of like a desire to get back
into making things for yourself?
>> You know, I was lost. I had taken quite
a bit of time off from making stuff.
With the exception of I had been doing a
good amount of voice work during that
time just to kind of scratch the itch,
things like, you know, Sad Cat Diary,
and then that became a commercial for
Purina called Dear Kitten, which is
um fairly widely known. Sort of another
example of like trying to make something
pop without relying on your own
>> Yeah.
>> Uh-huh.
>> what's prior. But I was very lost. That
was sort of like a roulette wheel
stopping moment, you know, where you're
just like, "Whoa." And and in that
particular thing, I wasn't
anywhere. I You know, I'd landed in the
middle of the
the board. I wasn't anywhere.
>> Can you tell me a little bit more about
your roulette wheel metaphor here? So,
you're the ball.
>> Yeah.
>> When you land, it's just like when
suddenly you're not moving.
>> Yeah, it's like the outside world has
stopped the wheel, has stopped the
possibility of the wheel. In my mind,
you know,
in the most fun state, you're bouncing
from idea to idea. There you know,
you're you're trying lots of different
things. You have this
>> you like land in the place where like
finally you know what the situation is
and you're like, "Okay, it's a 32." I
don't know how many things there are on
a roulette wheel. It's like suddenly
you're stopped and you're like, "Oh, I'm
here now. I'm stuck until somebody gives
me another spin."
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
>> So, you landed. And I mean, was there
some amount of like maybe people felt
differently about you? You'd been
through a lot of hard contentious
conversations, people who you used to
like didn't like you anymore. Were like
that kind of thing?
Or uh was there like some amount of
I not not knowing where you were?
>> Yeah, I I think it was like just not
knowing, you know, where I was. I think
that what you're talking about, which
is,
you know, you have sort of internal
representations of what the world is in
relationship to you, right? Who do
people think I am or what do they expect
from me? I mean, these are all you're
inventing them. You know,
they're they're inventions. And there's
times where
>> a lot to me.
>> Right, but I mean, they're inventions
like you can't know. I mean, this is in
the beginning of David Mitchell's book
Unruly, he writes a great thing about
history. He's like, what you know, what
is history anyways? It's like,
you know, if you if you contemplate now
and the billions of nows that are taking
place and the complexity of that, it's
unfathomable. And then we somehow want
to tell the story of now is evolving
into other nows and a lot of times when
you're
in a time of transition, when you don't
have as much strength, internal
strength, those thoughts can be a little
harder and a little [clears throat] more
consuming because they feel like a
pressure, they feel more real.
And certainly at that time, from the
perspective of like, okay, what do I do
next, there was this idea of like, oh
no, I'm I'm somebody who leads media
companies. Like, I mean, I think this
was a little bit of a fallacy that I ran
into becoming a business person, but I
have important ideas that can help
people blah blah blah. But that's not
really like how it works, you know?
Like, you find yourself in in certain
positions because of a trajectory. And
then when you're cast out of those
positions
and into a new space, you can't just
transplant that somewhere else. You have
to go on another journey. You have to
keep moving. Unless you're really like
institutional. Unless you like vibe off
the bureaucracy.
>> Yeah, yeah. I mean, you probably could
have got a job in media somewhere.
>> Yeah, maybe, but it was
it was a time where I guess I didn't
know what I what I really needed. So,
True Facts was there
and it was something that I did enjoy
doing and liked revisiting.
>> It's interesting because True Facts is
such a microcosm of how an idea works
where you put it out into the world and
then like as it interfaces with the
world, it changes. You wouldn't want to
try and like find where you are now
first.
Cuz you'd never know where you would end
up. You have to like have the idea be
exposed to air.
And like be good the whole time.
But then it ends up in a different place
than maybe you would have expected.
>> Yeah, I think that's true. I mean, I do
think that becoming is the point and you
can't have
a strong view about that trajectory.
Uh even True Facts, like True Facts is a
dining format, right? I mean, like
Shorts has almost disseminated the uh
view profile on it.
>> Um
>> Sure.
>> You know, just in terms of discovery.
I've decided to forego sponsors now. I
don't I don't like doing that. So, from
an economic standpoint, uh I know that
you recently uh moved to a non-profit
model. Most likely, I'm going to do the
same.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh True Facts isn't totally economically
viable anymore. So, I'm now I mean, I I
love that work and I and I am now pretty
committed to conservation and to the
love of animals and science about
animals. So, I want to keep that going,
but I am, you know, sort of thinking
about, "Okay, so what is next?" I'm
right back to that spot again of having
to, you know, reimagine and
you know, think things.
You had said that these episodes end
with a question.
>> Mhm.
>> And I think it'd be an an appropriate
time for you to read that question
because in this, [laughter] I think that
there's
there's a response to that question.
>> So, the question that we had was is is
what's something that you have learned
from this work that you wish everyone on
Earth knew?
>> You aren't a static thing.
You know, you change a lot
over time. You have a concept of of
yourself. You kind of imagine that
there's a stasis through time. I
recently listened to a recording of
myself with my friends that I made when
I was 18. I was like, "Who the
>> [laughter]
>> [__] is that? Like, what is that? What
what what And so, you know, you have
this idea of yourself as being kind of
consistent through time, but I don't
think that that's true.
>> I don't either.
>> For me, it's been really important to
say like, "Show up for the person who
you are that day."
>> Mhm.
>> And
you know, accept that you are different.
And
you know, if you can
when you feel yourself being
disappointed that you don't have the
passion that you had a day ago, a week
ago, or you're not finding the beauty in
something that that you had decided was
really important. You know, it's easy to
go into a place of loss or or less than
and then, you know, fight against the
current to get back to that.
But showing up for yourself and saying,
"Okay, all right, now I'm like this and
you know, I have to get this thing done
and it's not going to be enjoyable."
And you have to be okay with that. And
it's like, "Okay, what are you looking
forward to then? If that's not going to
satisfy you, what's one thing today that
hits where you are now and you're going
to be excited to get that done or
explore it?" Having that kind of a
framework
I think puts you into this
into the flow better.
>> Mhm.
>> And I'll give you the second correlate
to that, which is very idea
that you can understand
where you are points to the idea that
there's another part of you inside that
can sense that.
So, there is something that's static in
us.
Now, that voice, I call it the manager.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, we're getting into into
consciousness now?
>> It's my consciousness anyways.
>> No, I feel the same way and like when
you start to try and like pull the
pieces out from each other, you realize
that they are actually different things.
>> Yeah.
>> That like the thing that I think of as
myself is actually a bunch of different
things all kind of working together,
which is very weird. But yes, the
manager.
>> I've got one voice that is kind of like
a little older sounding, you know, it's
>> [laughter]
>> the voice is like
Hey bud. Hey bud.
>> Oh.
>> Yeah, this this isn't going to work.
>> I need this guy.
>> Yeah, it's like hey bud, this isn't
going to work. You know what you got to
do here. Or like whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa,
settle down. Like you're pressed up
against the glass. Like that's the other
That's the the side of me that I have to
combat quite a bit is there's this other
experience that I have of the world in
which is like a little boy pressed like
literally right up against the glass and
it's like oh [__] like life's coming at
him and he's not prepared. And a lot of
times the manager has to come in and be
like yo bud, just step back from the
glass. I got it. But the sort of
development of recognizing that you have
different capacities at different times,
that different things are going to give
you, you know, different satisfactions
is super helpful because it also helps
you take advice. Because a lot of times,
you know, it's great advice, but it has
nothing to do with how you are now. Like
>> [laughter]
>> pocket it. Put it in for later when
you're that guy, you know?
>> I definitely feel that. I ran up against
it when I got sick, when I got diagnosed
with cancer and and started going
through treatment.
This like reality that like all of the
things that I thought were so consistent
were not. Like the ways that I thought I
would react to that kind of news were
not the ways that I ended up reacting.
I think that this is a case of a lot of
times with serious illness or, you know,
injury, you
the hardest part it can often be the
challenge to the self. The realization
that you are maybe not who you thought
you were or you don't have all the same
strengths that you thought you had. But
I have
you know, I also gave this talk, you
know, 10 years ago
called [__] your dreams
that was about like you don't have to go
and achieve the dreams of your former
self just because your former self had
them if your current self doesn't
anymore.
I'm not saying they're bad, but like if
you get close to them or if and like
they aren't actually your dreams
anymore,
like live for you. Don't live for some
version of you who doesn't exist anymore
and is probably dumber because they have
fewer experiences.
>> Yeah, I agree with that.
So the last time we texted, you know,
it's right above when you asked me to be
on the podcast, I had just undergone
emergency colon surgery. I would have
had a near-death kind of thing.
I mean, I think to some degree we share
that experience,
you know, as as maybe
a foundational moment in
having to reconcile
the day-to-day of what goes on inside
your head, right? We're both people that
are outward quite a bit. We deal with
the world. We have thoughts about the
world. We make things for other people
to to enjoy. But those moments, there is
a kind of a weird clarity that comes out
of it. When you're faced with oh, okay,
yeah, it's me in here.
>> Mhm.
>> I can kind of like say whatever I want.
Like inside you can, right? I mean, I
was thinking that, you know, everybody
talks about their last words or people's
last words. And I was kind of cracking
up and I was like, oh, actually your
last words are yourself.
>> Yeah, nobody hears that.
>> I was cracking up and I because I was
like it would be funny if you like
really wanted your last thought to be a
thing and then you, you know, you were
close to death and you just kept
thinking it and then intrusive thoughts
came in. And you're like, [laughter]
some like dumb memory and you're like,
"No! No!" Like
>> That same loop that you've been on, like
just just like a vocal stim, the
clitoris explains it all theme. Yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah, [laughter] exactly. Exactly.
Yeah, and even this, you know, like what
we're talking right now is sort of later
life stuff. Like you don't have to
really think about it or worry about it
when you're young and pumped full of
brain hormones and like things that are
driving you
in all sorts of different directions.
>> Yeah, I mean, I don't know how old you
are, but in another 10 years perhaps I
will upload a video and not not be
obsessed with the immediate response.
>> I wouldn't have thought you as somebody
that that thought of it that way.
>> Yeah, well, now you think less of me and
that's [music] okay.
>> No, no, not at all.
>> Thanks to all the humans who helped make
this episode. [music]
Morgan Levy is the show's supervising
producer and Greg Rippin is our
engineer. Peyton Mitchell manages our
social media, Andrew Huang composed the
music, and James Barnard designed
[music] the artwork. You can and should
follow us wherever you listen to
podcasts.
>> Let's do it one more time.
>> Humans.